<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-hall July 30, 1676 by John Meriton ...</title>
            <author>Meriton, John, b. ca. 1630.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1677</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1821</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R744</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12770156</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12770156</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93637</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93637)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 699:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-hall July 30, 1676 by John Meriton ...</title>
                  <author>Meriton, John, b. ca. 1630.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Simon Miller ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1677.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew III, 8-9 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93637:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING, AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>July</hi> 30. 1676.</p>
            <p>By <hi>John Meriton,</hi> M. A. Chaplain to the Right Honourable HENRY, Earl of <hi>Arlington,</hi> Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain of His Majeſty's Houſhold.</p>
            <p>Printed by His Majeſty's ſpecial Command.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Simon Miller,</hi> at the Star at the Weſt-end of St. <hi>Paul's.</hi> 1677.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:93637:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93637:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MATTH. iii. 8, 9.</bibl>
                  <p>Bring forth therefore fruits meet for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
                  <p>And think not to ſay within your ſelves, We have Abraham to our Father; for I ſay unto you, that God is able of theſe ſtones, to raiſe up children unto Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words were ſpoken to the Phariſees and Sadduces, who were the great Zealots of the Jewiſh Church; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Phariſees, whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calls <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the moſt ſtrait Sect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Jews, <hi>Act.</hi> 26. 5. Which knew me from the beginning (if they would teſtifie) that after the moſt ſtrait Sect of our Religion, I liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Phariſee. Theſe were zealous and pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93637:3"/>
in the obſervation of the Law of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and all other Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies inſtituted of God by <hi>Moſes:</hi> under which for a time, were contained the Myſteries of true Religion and Godlineſs; <hi>Heb.</hi> 9. 9, 10. which was a figure for the time then preſent, in which were offered both gifts and ſacrifices for ſin; which could not make him that did that ſervice perfect, as pertaining to the Conſcience: Which ſtood in meats and drinks, and divers waſhings and carnal Ordinances; impoſed on them only until the time of Reformation. In which Inſtitutions conſiſted the external Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Form of true Religion, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Communion with the viſible Church, until the coming of Chriſt in the Fleſh: but by a blind zeal for the Form, without the Power of Godlineſs, the Phariſees and Sadducees thought themſelves privileged againſt the wrath menaced by the Baptiſt; which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained a Prophecy of the deſtruction of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and other great calamities then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching to the Jews under <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian,</hi> and alſo the terrour of eternal puniſhment in the damnation of Hell. The multitude came and were baptized of him in <hi>Jordan,</hi> confeſſing their ſins: but theſe righteous in their own
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93637:3"/>
eyes had no ſins to confeſs, and came only to his Baptiſm out of a vain curioſity to ſee and cenſure; deriding rather than believing that wrath they were warned to flee from; reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (as is evident from the Baptiſt's words in the Text,) We are zealous of the Law of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, and all things enjoyned us of God by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and have <hi>Abraham</hi> to our Father: Tuſh, God cannot deſtroy us, being righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; nor according to the Oath which he ſware to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed for ever: but with <hi>Ixi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in the Fable, they embraced a Cloud inſtead of <hi>Juno;</hi> whilſt they thought they had found the cleareſt and the brighteſt truth, it proved but a Cloud of palpable errour and darkneſs. For the Baptiſt accuſes their Righteouſneſs of inſufficiency, admoniſhes them to repent, and upbraids their vain oftentation, and fruitleſs boaſting of ſucceſſion from <hi>Abraham;</hi> from whoſe faith and vertue they were ſo far dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, as they were more like a brood of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers than his Children. They had proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all this while upon a falſe Hypotheſis, about that Righteouſneſs, wherein conſiſted the power and ſubſtance of true Religion and Godlineſs; and upon which the Covenant of God in Chriſt was confirmed to <hi>Abraham,</hi> four
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93637:4"/>
hundred and thirty years before the giving of the Law by <hi>Moſes, Gal.</hi> 3. 15, 16. So that unleſs they would now upon means of better information, recant their errours, and recall their miſtakes, and reform their manners; which is indeed to repent; they could not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themſelves from being involved in the common Miſeries, then approaching their Land and Countrey, under <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Veſpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> or for ever eſcape the damnation of Hell. For the Promiſe that he ſhould be Heir of the world, was not to <hi>Abraham</hi> or to his ſeed through the law, but through the righteouſneſs of faith. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 13. Religion is not a Complement, but a real thing; and that righteouſneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we are righteous in the ſight of God, is not external obedience of the body to inſtitut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Righteouſneſs, or poſitive Laws; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal obedience of the heart, to the Law of Moral goodneſs, and the Dictates of right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon engraven upon the conſcience of every man; <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 14. Explained and made more evident by the ſeveral Revelations of God, who at ſundry times, and in divers manners, ſpake in times paſt to the Fathers by the Prophets; and in theſe laſt days unto us by his Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 1. The former, which is our righteouſneſs
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93637:4"/>
in the ſight of men, and but the ſhadow and carcaſe of Religion; is called a righteouſneſs of our own, which is according to the Law, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 9. As being the performance of the letter of the Law, by the act and operation of the body, through mere natural vertue, which is our own. But the latter, which is our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs in the ſight of God; is called in the ſame Text, The righteouſneſs which is of God by faith in Jeſus Chriſt: Of which words I think my ſelf obliged to give a diſtinct and full account (and that according to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of truth to my own Conſcience in the ſight of God;) they being the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our preſent life, to a future happineſs; which makes an errour dangerous, and truth to be valued in opening them: then I muſt give ſolution to theſe three Particulars; 1. In what ſence called the righteouſneſs of Faith. 2. Of God. 3. Of God by faith in Jeſus Chriſt. 1. It is called the righteouſneſs of Faith in a double reſpect: 1. As being the moſt proper object of our Belief, ſo to conceive of God, as is moſt agreeable to natural notice, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Revelation. 2. As being the only Principle to the practice of all the Duties and Obligations of the Will of God ſo revealed;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93637:5"/>
Faith being the firſt Principle of all Religion, both natural and revealed; <hi>Heb</hi> 11. 6. He that comes to God muſt believe that he is, and that he is the rewarder of them that diligently ſeek him. 2. It is called the righteouſneſs of God, 1. As being the Copy or Image of that righteouſneſs, which God is in himſelf; of which God himſelf is the Original and Perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. 2. As being that righteouſneſs which God only approves, and will reward: <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 28. He is not a Jew, which is one outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; nor is Circumciſion that which is outward in the fleſh, but that which is inward in the heart; whoſe praiſe is not of Men, but of God. 3. It is called the Righteouſneſs of God by Faith in Jeſus Chriſt: 1. As to the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of which, we are aſſiſted by the grace of God, obtained by faith in Jeſus Chriſt (in whoſe Name, whatſoever we ask, believing, we ſhall receive) and the grace of the new Covenant conſiſts in theſe three things; 1. To encline our wills to accept the conditions. 2. Upon our acceptance, to aſſiſt our weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 3. To accept our ſincerity through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny defects and imperfections: the integrity of our Wills will ſo far commute for the deed, that is, for the perfection of obedience to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93637:5"/>
that Law of Moral Righteouſneſs in a State of Grace; as whatever pollutions or defilements we may have contracted through the fraud of the Devil, the frailty of the Fleſh, or tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the World. So long as our Converſe with bodily Objects, have not altogether ſunk down our ſouls into a vicious love of them, which is the dregs and feculency of ſin and folly; God will accept us upon a ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, through the Merit and Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Holy Jeſus: the redundancy of whoſe righteouſneſs is to ſupply the defects of a ſincere repentance. 2. As being that righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, in the purſuance of which in truth, though we cannot in perfection, we can only have confidence of acceptance with God, through Jeſus Chriſt: though we cannot be golden Scepters, we muſt be broken Reeds; though not burning and ſhining Lights, we muſt be ſmoaking Flaxes in his ſight; who will not break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoaking flax, until judgment be brought forth unto victory. And this is that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Faith, wherein conſiſts the power and ſubſtance of true Religion and Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; upon which, as the condition, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of our reconciliation and happineſs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93637:6"/>
was confirmed of God in Chriſt to <hi>Abraham,</hi> for all Generations; who received the ſign of Circumciſion, but as the Seal of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs of Faith, (which is the condition of the Covenant) which he had yet being uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, that he might be the Father of all that believe; that righteouſneſs might be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to them alſo, though they were not cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. So that God was in no need of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s Children according to the fleſh; but could, without breach of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to him (upon their Apoſtacy and Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy from his faith and righteouſneſs) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them all; and out of the obdurate Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile world, or the very ſtones, raiſe up a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to himſelf, followers of the faith of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham;</hi> to whom, as ſuch, the Promiſe in Chriſt did as truly belong, as to the proudeſt Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee or Sadducee of them all. Circumciſion was but the ſign of the Covenant, not obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to it; but the profeſſion of Religion, not the practice of it: and for them only to profeſs and expect the reward, was as prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous, as if a Servant ſhould demand wages of his Maſter for wearing of his Livery, and neglecting of his Work. The faith and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of <hi>Abraham</hi> was example for their
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93637:6"/>
vertue, not expiation of their ſin; and they might as reaſonably have expected to have liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed naturally, by vertue of what <hi>Abraham</hi> had eat and drank, without eating and drinking for themſelves, as to live eternally by vertue of that particular act of believing, whereby <hi>Abraham</hi> wrought the works of God, which was counted to him for righteouſneſs; unleſs by the ſame Spirit of Faith, they ſhould work the works of <hi>Abraham</hi> and of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by work out their own Salvation with fear and trembling: for <hi>Abraham</hi>'s righteouſneſs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined in himſelf, he could thereby but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver his own ſoul; for God reſpects no man for the goodneſs of another, but every man in the circumſtance of his own integrity: If the Stones, the obdurate Gentiles, the Wild O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lives grafted in, will believe and repent, and do the works of <hi>Abraham</hi> upon the hearing of the Goſpel; they ſhall be the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and Heirs according to the Promiſe: and if the Jews, the Natural Branches, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in their Hardneſs and Unbelief, it ſhall be no privilege to them, that they are the Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring of <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the fleſh: <hi>Bring forth therefore fruits meet for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: And think not to ſay within your</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93637:7"/>
               <hi>ſelves, we have Abraham to our Father; for I ſay unto you, that God is able of theſe ſtones to raiſe up children unto Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Words thus opened, principally imply two Particulars, by way of Motive to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: 1. The Univerſality of the purpoſe of the Grace of God in the Redemption of the world by Jeſus Chriſt; the moſt proper Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to Repentance againſt Deſpair. 2. The Impartiality of God's Juſtice, in diſtributing Rewards and Puniſhments without reſpect of perſons; (<hi>And think not to ſay within your ſelves, we have Abraham to our Father</hi>) the moſt proper Motive to Repentance againſt carnal ſecurity and preſumption. God is impartially good that none may deſpair, and impartially juſt that none may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume. 1. God is impartially good: Though the Jews were Iſraelites, to whom appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Adoption, and the Glory, and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, and the giving of the Law, and the Promiſes; whoſe were the Fathers, and of whom, as concerning the Fleſh, Chriſt came, who is God bleſſed for ever, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 4. And to whom were committed the Oracles of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 2. God had not therefore caſt off all care or concern for other Nations; though
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93637:7"/>
he had left them for ſome time, to walk in their own ways, without the direction of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Righteouſneſs, or poſitive Laws; yet he did not leave himſelf without Witneſs, in that he did them good, and gave them rain from heaven, and fruitful Seaſons; filling their hearts with food and gladneſs, <hi>Acts</hi> 14. 17. And though the coming of Chriſt in the fleſh, that he might reconcile both Jew and Gentile unto God in one Body by the Croſs, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. 16. And that the Gentiles ſhould be Fellow-Heirs with the Jews of the ſame Body, and partakers together of the Promiſes of Chriſt by the Goſpel, was a Notion that had been for ſome time buried in the dark vault of Nature's Ruines, and long obſcured under the thick veil of <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Law, and by the dark ſayings of the Prophets concerning Chriſt, ſo as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtles to the <hi>Epheſians</hi> and <hi>Coloſſians, Epheſ.</hi> 3. 4, 5. <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1. 26. calls it a Myſtery which hath been hid from Ages and Generations: And St. <hi>Peter,</hi> the Miniſter of the Circumciſion and great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle of the Jews, was firſt warranted by a Viſion from Heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 28. before he would acknowledge any Grace of God to the Gentiles; yet what was formerly drawn by a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93637:8"/>
dark Coal or Pencil, is now written with a Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beam; and there is no difference between the Jew and the Greek, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 12. God can be merciful without being partial, juſt without being cruel, and truly great without deſigning irreſpectively the far greateſt part of Mankind, for the Trophies of his Power, in an eternal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery: For, as it follows in the ſame Text, the ſame Lord over all, is rich unto all that call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. God is equally related unto Mankind as the ſame Lord, he is the God of the ſpirits of all fleſh, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 9. And hath made of one Blood all Nations of men, to dwell on all the face of the earth; and hath determined the times before appointed, and the bounds of their habitations: <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 26. His Hands faſhioned <hi>Eſau</hi> as well as <hi>Jacob;</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently obliges his love and care in truth, though not in degree for both: ſo that thoſe words, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 13. <hi>Jacob</hi> have I loved, and <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hated, reſpect not the perſons of <hi>Eſau</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> but their Poſterities; as is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident to all unprejudiced minds, from that place of the Prophet <hi>Malachi,</hi> 1. 1, 2, 3. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to by the Apoſtle; the words are, The burden of the Word of the Lord to <hi>Iſrael</hi> by <hi>Malachi;</hi> I have loved you, ſaith the Lord,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:93637:8"/>
yet ye ſay, wherein haſt thou loved us? Was not <hi>Eſau Jacob</hi>'s Brother, ſaith the Lord? yet I loved <hi>Jacob,</hi> and hated <hi>Eſau;</hi> and laid his Mountains &amp; his Heritage waſte for the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons of the Wilderneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So that the true meaning of the expreſſions, <hi>Jacob</hi> have I lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hated, is comparative and gradual with reſpect only to grace and favour, and not at all to ill will or hate; and may be rendred, <hi>Jacob</hi> have I preferred in my favour before <hi>Eſau,</hi> in giving his Poſterity the good Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and that of <hi>Eſau's</hi> the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Mountains. And that theſe expreſſions were thus uſually underſtood amongſt the Jews, is evident by thoſe words of the ſame Dialect of our Saviour's, <hi>Luke,</hi> 14. 26. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man come to me, and hate not his Father and Mother, and his own life; Where Hate cannot refer to ill-will properly, but to a leſs degree of love; unleſs we can ſuppoſe our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour to cancel the bonds of natural affection, and extinguiſh the common Principles of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: And although our common relation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, introduce no Anabaptiſtical parity or community in his favours, but <hi>Jacob</hi> have I loved, and <hi>Eſau</hi> have I hated; yet it maintains his good will towards all, and ſecures every
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93637:9"/>
man from being miſerable, that with hearty repentance and true faith turn unto him. And this is a repreſentation worthy of God and Chriſt, worthy the infinite goodneſs and grace of God, who is not ſtraitned by ſaving a few or many, as if he could ſave no more; who is able to ſave unto the utmoſt all that come unto him in Jeſus Chriſt: for he is a Fountain of Living Water, and can quench the thirſt of all men and creatures without drawing himſelf dry; his goodneſs, like the Sun, enlightens every Star, and influences every Plant, without abatement of his own vertue or light; he is the true <hi>Moſes</hi>'s Buſh, that burns without waſte, warms and enlivens eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing without conſuming or impairing his own heat or beams: and it is a light thing for him (that is, an undervaluing of his Power and Goodneſs) as he ſaith by his Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> to raiſe up the Tribes of <hi>Jacob,</hi> and reſtore the preſerved of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> therefore have I giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en him (that is, Chriſt) that he might be for Salvation unto the ends of the Earth: and as they do but eclipſe the glory of the Sun in the Firmament, who reſtrain his light and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to ſome few Regions and Countreys, and extend them not from the riſing, to the going
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93637:9"/>
down of the ſame; ſo do they the Riches of the Grace of God, who confine it to a few, and extend it not to Mankind. It is alſo no leſs worthy of the infinite Merit of the Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of Chriſt; who, by his own Oblation of himſelf once offered upon the Croſs, made a full, perfect and ſufficient Sacrifice, Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Satisfaction, for the ſins of the whole world; and can we deem without ſcandal and imputation to his Satisfaction, the Merit of our Second <hi>Adam</hi> leſs powerful to redeem, than the guilt of the Firſt <hi>Adam</hi> was to capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and enthral? So that as by the offence of one Judgment came upon all men to Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation; ſo by the righteouſneſs of one, the free Gift is come upon all men to juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of life, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 18.</p>
            <p>And as for that Objection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 18. For who hath reſiſted his Will: If God's Will muſt be accompliſhed, and God hath willed the Salvation of all men by Jeſus Chriſt, how comes it to paſs that any periſh?</p>
            <p>Be it conſidered for anſwer hereunto, That God hath willed the Salvation of all men by Jeſus Chriſt, through the Conditions of Faith and Repentance; and ſo his Will is unreſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all that are ſaved, and in all that periſh.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93637:10"/>
Chriſt died, by the Will of God, for all that believe and repent; but all that believe not, but remain impenitent, periſh everlaſtingly; which is the fault of their own impenitence and infidelity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Nor can our Faith or Infidelity make the Will of God of no effect; and ſuch is the concurrence of God's Grace with every man's Will, who works in us to will and to do of His own good pleaſure, whereby every man may, if he will, work out his own Salvation with fear and trembling; nor can our acceptance or refuſal of his Grace prejudice or leſſen his good Will; the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or contumely of the Patient, cannot juſtly derogate from the kindneſs of the Phyſician, or Sovereignty of the Remedy; nor are the Riches of God's Grace leſs in themſelves, though multitudes continue poor only becauſe they will not, and deſpiſe: And God is ſtill the Saviour of all men, though eſpecially or actually only of them that believe, becauſe he is not really willing that any ſhould periſh, but rather that all ſhould come to Repentance; his Nature and Property is always to have mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and to forgive all that believe and repent; and he is unwillingly compelled to deſtroy the Impenitent and Unbelieving; and he is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93637:10"/>
thirſty after no mans blood, who hath grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto all Repentance unto Life; and his ways are equal, who leaves every man to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit his own Choice, and renders to every man according to his works, without reſpect of perſons; which is the next Particular to be diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>For, Although Mercy and Free Grace admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted lapſed Mankind to Conditions of Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and Reſtitution by Jeſus Chriſt; yet Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice exacts the performance of thoſe conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and accordingly diſtributes Rewards and Puniſhments: for the Grace of God is a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, and a Covenant without a Condition, is a Contradiction; and unleſs the Conditions be performed, can it reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be expected there ſhould be any force or vertue in the Obligation. And in this ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate and impartial dealing of God, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gards not the merit of the <hi>Opus operatum,</hi> or or thing done by us, but the Equity and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of his own Promiſe and Covenant; who hath eſtabliſhed a reward infinitely exceeding the Merit of the Obedience required, either as congruous or condign from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Work wrought; which is but a juſt compliance with the Will of our Lawful
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93637:11"/>
Sovereign, who hath power of Right to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and it is but our duty to obey; ſo that when we have done all, we are but unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Servants, becauſe we have done no more than was our duty to perform; and whatever is of duty, implies no reward as of Deſert or Merit, but only from that Grace which hath annexed a reward to our duty, to make it our intereſt to obey. So that it is a righteous thing with God, to reward and crown our obedience to his Laws in Chriſt (whence called a Crown of Righteouſneſs) not for the Righteouſneſs of our Work, but his own Promiſe; indeed, what is there in us or our ſervices, worthy that Eternal Happineſs which he hath promiſed, as the reward of of his Grace to a ſincere Repentance, ſince both the Will and the Deed is from his Grace, who works in us to will and to do, of his own good pleaſure, <hi>Philip.</hi> 2. 13. So that after we, through God, having done the will of God; what remains for God to reward in us, but his own Gifts and Graces? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> who renders to every man according to, though not for, his works; and with him is no reſpect of perſons. Evident with reſpect, 1. To the Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Nature; who is free from all ſuch
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93637:11"/>
Defects and Imperfections, as are incident to Humane Natures; whereby Judgment is often turned into Gall, and Righteouſneſs into Hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock; the Wicked are juſtified, and the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous condemned, (both which are alike Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to the Lord,) and Juſtice frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impartially adminiſtred in this Life. Thus <hi>Saul</hi> ſpared <hi>Agag,</hi> and the beſt of the Spoil of the Amalekites, when he ſhould have deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them all, out of Covetouſneſs, or Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, or both, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 8. Thus <hi>Eli</hi> ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reproved his Sons, when he ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenced their ſin with death (which was great before the Lord) through natural ſond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 23. But God is free from all ſuch Weakneſſes and Imperfections, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with him is no reſpect of perſons: which will yet more evidently appear, with reſpect to the Immutability of his Will; who is not as a Man, that he ſhould change, or as the Son of Man, that he ſhould repent; God is free from all ſuch grounds and cauſes, as render Humane Wills ſubject to alteration, as Ignorance and Impotence. Men often change their Wills for want of diſcretion to chuſe no better, and for want of a preſent clear diſcerning and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview of things. Men are often forced to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93637:12"/>
After-games of Prudence, which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Notion of Repentance; but God hath an Intuitive Knowledge, and ſees all things as they are and ſhall be in time from all Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
            <p>Men frequently change their wills whether they will or no: the Rational Faculty of the Soul is ſometimes captivated through force and violence; but who can reſiſt his Will, who is Omnipotent, to whom all Nations are as the drop of a Bucket, and as the ſmall duſt of the Ballance? and the concurrent ſtrength of created Power, but as the Withs, wherewith the Philiſtines bound <hi>Sampſon;</hi> as a Thred of Tow, when it toucheth the fire, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as for that Objection which ſome urge againſt the Immutability of the Divine Will, from ſuch Scriptures as ſeem to aſcribe Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to God; as, <hi>Joel,</hi> 2. 14. <hi>Jonah,</hi> 3. 10. Who knows if he may repent? be it conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the threatnings of God are conditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; and when not expreſſed, are ever imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, according to that Maxime of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> 18. 7, 8, 9. At what inſtant I ſhall ſpeak concerning a Nation, and concerning a Kingdom; to pluck up, and to pull down, and to deſtroy it: if that Nation, againſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93637:12"/>
whom I have pronounced, turn from their evil, then I will repent of the evil that I thought to do unto them. So that it being the Immutable Will of God to repent of the Evil of Puniſhment upon Man's repenting of the Evil of Sin; <hi>Penitere est ſententiam muta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, to repent is but to change his Sentence,</hi> but not the Will, the Will ſtill remaining with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out variableneſs, or ſhadow of turning: And the immutability of his Will eſtabliſheth the truth of his diſtributing Rewards and Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, according to every man's work, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect of perſons; and that he regards not the Perſons of men, but the perſormance of the Conditions, upon which he hath eſtabliſhed the Covenant of our Reconciliation and Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs by Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The proper Inferences now, from this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe are,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Encouragement; and Secondly, Caution.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Encouragement for every man to make good his Intereſt in the Common Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Indeed, who would ſweat in the Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Grace, and bleed in Conflict with Sin, if after he hath done the Will of God, he
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93637:13"/>
muſt remain uncertain whether he ſhall inherit the Promiſe. This is that detains the Devils in Impenitence, who believe and tremble, <hi>James,</hi> 2. 19. becauſe they are reſerved in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Chains under Darkneſs, to the Judgment of the Laſt Day, <hi>Jude,</hi> 6. But though Chriſt took not on him the Nature of Angels, he hath of the Seed of <hi>Abraham;</hi> and all that do the Works of <hi>Abraham,</hi> are the Children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and Heirs according to the Promiſe. Then let no man ſay with thoſe in <hi>Jeremy,</hi> 18. 12. There is no hope, but we will walk after our own devices, and every man do the imagination of his evil heart: But let the Wicked forſake his way, and the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous man his thoughts; and turn unto God, for he is gracious; and unto our God, for he will abundantly pardon: And let every man work out his own Salvation with fear and trembling; leſt a Promiſe being left, any man ſeem to come ſhort of it, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Caution: 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 17. Since we call on the Father; who, without reſpect of perſons, judgeth according to every man's work, to paſs the time of our ſojourning here in fear; and repoſe no more confidence of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity from Succeſſion from Holy men, than
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:93637:13"/>
as we are followers of their Faith and Virtues; nor in the ſtrict and zealous performance of all inſtituted Righteouſneſs and poſitive Laws, then as they are productive of the main end of purifying our hearts by faith; renewing us in the Spirit of our minds, and cloathing us with that New Man, which after God, is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs; and the end of the Commandment is Charity, out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and Faith unfeigned, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 5. And, as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, the Law (that is, Poſitive Law, is not for a righteous man, in whom the Law of Nature lives; and can perform the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of it, without the help of outward Laws: for the deſign of all inſtituted Righteouſneſs, and poſitive Laws, is but to conform us to the Duties and Obligations of the Law of Moral Righteouſneſs; and all obedience to them is no farther acceptable, than as it is inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and ſerviceable to that great purpoſe. And God is ſo far from being pleaſed with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of Inſtituted Righteouſneſs in the guilt of Immoralities, as it is the great aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of his diſpleaſure and indignation; <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa.</hi> 1. 11. To what purpoſe is the multitude of your Sacrifices? bring no more vain Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93637:14"/>
your hands are full of blood: <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> 66. 3. He that kills an Ox, is as if he ſlew a Man; he that ſacrificeth a Lamb, as if he cut off a Dog's neck; he that offers an Oblation, as if he offered Swine's blood; he that burneth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, as if he bleſſed an Idol; whilſt they have choſen their own ways, and their ſouls delight in their Abominations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what-ever Veneration theſe righteous men in the Text had for themſelves, for tything Mint, Annice, and Cummin; but neglecting the weightier things of the Law, Judgment, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Faith; for making clean the outſide of the Cup and Platter, remaining within full of Extortion and Exceſs; making long Prayers to devour Widows Houſes: Our Saviour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteems no better of them than whited Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres, which appear beautiful to the eye, but within are full of rottenneſs and dead men's bones: let our care be then to be real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what we appear; not having a Form of Godlineſs, denying the Power: and let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man that names the Name of Chriſt, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from all Iniquity; for bodily Exerciſe profits little, but Godlineſs hath the Promiſe of this life, and that that is to come.</p>
            <p>This is that Law of Perfection; which it is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93637:14"/>
the deſign of all poſitive Laws to advance and propagate, as the Promulgation of the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, and the Inſtitution of the Goſpel; which is ſo far from being a relaxation to Moral Duty, as it is the greateſt help and obligation to promote it, upon a twofold account;</p>
            <p>Firſt, As the moſt clear and manifeſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Truth; The Law came by <hi>Moſes,</hi> but Grace and Truth by Jeſus Chriſt: The Law was Truth in obſcure Types and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, but the Goſpel is Truth in its own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and Likeneſs: and the clearer and more manifeſtly any Law is promulged, the greater and more forcible is its Obligation; <hi>Acts,</hi> 17. 35. The time of this ignorance God winked at, but now he commands all men every where to repent.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As the moſt clear evidence of the truth and certainty of a future life after this, the main Argument of the Goſpel being the truth and certainty of the Reſurrection of Chriſt from the dead, in the truth and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Humane Nature, and in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Life and Immortality, to die no more; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 9. Who hath aboliſhed Death, and brought Life and Immortality to light, through the Goſpel. The Summary
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:93637:15"/>
Article of which is to confeſs with our mouths the Lord Jeſus, and believe in our hearts that God hath raiſed him from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 10. God hath been pleaſed to give many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of his Power, in raiſing the Dead by his Prophets under the Law, and by Chriſt and his Apoſtles under the Goſpel; which are ſtrong Inferences of the poſſibility of a Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection: but becauſe all that were raiſed from the dead (till Chriſt) dyed again, and he only lives to die no more. His being ſo raiſed is the only aſſurance, as the Firſt Fruits of a full Harveſt of a future Reſurrection and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; when every man ſhall riſe again with his own Body, to receive according to what he hath done in the Fleſh, whether good or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil: and the belief of this is the moſt (if not only) powerful Motive to Moral Goodneſs; for if there be no Reſurrection, it is a Natural Inference, Let us eat and drink, for to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row we die. But if there be a Reſurrection, it is equally rational to infer: herein let us exerciſe our ſelves continually, to have always a Conſcience void of offence towards God, and towards man. The Jews were generally governed by the hope and fear of Reward and Puniſhment only in this life; and generally
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93637:15"/>
looked for a Temporal <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> to deliver them from the bondage of the Roman Tyranny, and to give them great temporal Peace and Proſperity: and becauſe Chriſt came in the weakneſs and poverty of a Servant, and they expected him in the pomp and power of a Sovereign, they owned him not for their <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> but to this day look for another; the which their Errours and Miſpritions, were the Genuine Off ſpring of their ignorance and uncertainty of a Future State. And the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducees, a great and learned Party amongſt them, ſaid there is no Reſurrection, neither Angel nor Spirit. And though the Gentiles (at leaſt ſome of their wiſe men and Philoſophers) aſſerted and believed the Immortality of the Soul, yet they were all uncertain, if not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in unbelief, of the Reſurrection of the Body: that theſe <hi>Mola</hi>'s of fleſh and blood ſhould put on Incorruption, and be cloathed with Immortality; which is the only clear Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation of the Goſpel, and the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Argument to all the Duties and Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Moral Righteouſneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Jews went into Captivity under <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſack</hi> King of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> King of <hi>Babel;</hi> and at laſt, were deſolate under <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:93637:16"/>
and <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> with the Temple of the Lord in their mouths, and the ſign of Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion in their fleſh, and <hi>Abraham</hi> to their Father. And if God ſpared not the Natural Branches, it is fair warning to the Wild Olives grafted in not to be high minded, but fear; not to truſt to the outward Privileges of the due Adminiſtration of the Word and Sacraments, or external obedience to Inſtituted Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and poſitive Laws, without cleanſing themſelves from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, perfecting holineſs in the fear of God; for it is not that that goes in, but that that comes out, that defiles a man: Good and Evil pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly conſiſts not in the external act and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Body, but in the inward habit and diſpoſition of the mind; whence it is, that love is the fulfilling of the Law; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, Hate, the tranſgreſſion of it: ſo that he that loves his Neighbour as himſelf, is his preſerver; and he that hates him in his heart, is his murtherer; though neither ever have power or opportunity actuallay either to ſave or to deſtroy. Charity is not properly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relieve them that want, but to love God above all, and our Neighbour as our ſelves; nor Martyrdome every dying, but dying for the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:93637:16"/>
love of God and Truth; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 3. And though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burned, and have not Charity, it profiteth me nothing: <hi>Joh.</hi> 4. 24. God is a Spirit, and they that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth: <hi>Optimus animus pulcherrimus Dei cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> Seneca; <hi>He worſhips God beſt, who hath the beſt mind.</hi> God bears reſpect to <hi>Abel</hi> and to his Offering. That Holocauſt and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which ſmokes from the Altar of a dovot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed heart to God (for the Altar ſanctifies the Gift) bears our acceptable Odour, otherwiſe we are but like Vaults, that ſound merely from their hollowneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>External Profeſſion of the beſt Religion, Outward Communion with the beſt Church, ſuch as the Jewiſh once was, and the Chriſtian now is; cannot ſecure or privilege from the ſtorms of Divine Vengeance, without the true belief, and neceſſry practice of Truth and Holineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince we have the Profeſſion of the beſt Religion, and live in Communion with one of the beſt Churches this day in the world (which happineſs God grant us long to enjoy, under the protection, and in the long life and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:93637:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
proſperity of our moſt religious and gracious Sovereign) (and may it ever be the Bleſſing to us, and our Poſterities for all Generations) that therein we may effectually ſave our ſouls from death, and hide the multitude of our ſins: may it pleaſe God ſo to aſſiſt us with his Grace, as that in the firm belief of all her Principles, &amp; in the uniform practice of all her Duties and Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we may lead quiet and peaceable lives in all Godlineſs and Honeſty; that being holy, and humble, and undefiled, the Children of God without rebuke, we may at laſt, together with all thoſe that are departed this world in the true Faith, and fear of God, be made partak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord Jeſus: To whom, with the Father, and the Holy Spirit; three Perſons, and one God, of the ſame Subſtance, Power and Eternity; be given of us, all Angels, all Men, and all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, all poſſible Honour and Glory, Praiſe and Dominion, Power and Thankſgiving, Fear, Adoration and Obedience, now and for ever; <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
